关于攻击分组密码，有大量文献
There is an immense literature on attacking block ciphers.
本节中，我想给大家看一看这些攻击长什么样
In this segment, I just want to give you a taste for
what these attacks look like.
我希望说服大家永远不要使用你自己设计的分组密码
And I hope I'll convince you that you should never
ever design your own block cipher,
坚持使用标准，比如3DES和AES
and just stick to the standards like Triple DES
and AES.
我想讨论的第一种类型的攻击
The first set of attacks that I want to talk about
是基于分组密码实现上的攻击
are attacks on the implementation of the block cipher.
比如说，设想你有一个智能卡，上面实现了一个分组密码
As an example, imagine you have a smart card that's implementing a block cipher.
那么这个智能卡可以被用来支付信用卡，比如说
So the smart card, for example, could be used for
credit card payments. It might have a
它内部可能含有一个密钥，用来认证你的信用卡支付
secret key inside of it to authenticate
your credit card payments as you stick the
当你把卡插入支付终端里。现在，如果一个攻击者获得了你的智能卡
card into a payment terminal, say. So now, if an attacker obtains your smart card,
他可以拿着这张智能卡到实验室里
what he could do is he could actually take
the smart card to a lab, and then run the
然后运行这张卡，非常精确地测量这张卡加密和解密的时间
card, and measure very precisely how much time the card took to do encryption and
这些加密花掉的时间
decryption. Now, if the amount of time that the implementation took to do
取决于密钥的内容，通过测量时间
encryption depends on bits of the secret
key, then by measuring the time, the
攻击者可以学习到你的密钥内容
attacker will learn something about your
secret key and in fact, he might be able
事实上，他可能可以完全提取出你的密钥。有很多例子
to completely extract your secret key. And
there are many examples of implementations
是通过非常精确地测量加密算法的时间
that simply by measuring the time very
precisely for many operations of
来完全提取密钥的。另一个例子是
encryption algorithms, you can completely
extract the secret key. Another example is,
不是测量时间，而是测量功耗
rather than just measuring the time, you
can actually measure the power consumption
当卡运行时的功耗。你可以联结一个设备
of the card as it's operating. So,
literally, you can connect it to a device
用来测量智能卡需要的电流
that will measure the current that the
card is drawing and then graph the
然后非常精确地记录电流。这些智能卡不是非常快
currents very, very precisely. Now, these
cards are not very fast, and as a result,
因此你可以测量每个时钟周期内的精确功耗
you can actually measure the exact amount
of power consumed at every clock cycle as
当智能卡运行时。届时你会得到类似这样的图
the card was executing. When you do that,
you actually get graphs of this form.
这是一个智能卡工作的例子
So this is an example of a smart card
operating, while it's doing the
当它在计算DES时。大家可以清楚地看到
DES computation. So you can see
very clearly, here's when it was doing
这是当它在进行初始置换时
这是当它在进行最终置换时
the initial permutation. Here's when it's
doing the final permutation. And then,
然后这里，大家可以数数，有16个峰值和谷
here, you can count. There are actually
sixteen hills and troughs
分别对应16轮回合。当像这样放大这张图时
corresponding to the sixteen rounds. And
essentially when you zoom in on a graph
你可以一位一位地读出来
like this, you can basically read the key
bits off one by one, just by looking at
就看智能卡的功耗变化，在做不同操作时
how much power the card consumed as it was
doing the different operations. It turns out
实际上，即使智能卡采取措施来屏蔽这种信息
that, even cards that take steps to mask
this type of information, are still
它依然是脆弱的。有一种攻击叫做差分功耗分析
vulnerable. There's an attack called differential power analysis, where
运行加密算法很多次，测量智能卡功耗
basically, you measure the power consumed
by the card over many, many, many, runs of
只要有电流上的小差异
the encryption algorithm. And as long as
there's any even small dependence between
密钥的各位的依赖性
the amount of current consumed and the
bits of the secret key, basically that
经过足够多的加密算法运行次数就能显现出来
dependence will show up after enough runs of the encryption algorithm. And as a
因此大家可以完全提取出密钥来。好
result you'll be able to completely
extract the secret key. Okay, so these
这些攻击实际上是Paul Kocher和他同事发现的
attacks were actually discovered by Paul
Kocher and his colleagues up at
在密码学研究所。工业界有很多技术
Cryptography Research and there's actually
a fairly large industry devoted to just
是用来抵抗这些功耗攻击的。如果考虑计时攻击
defending against these power attacks. As
far as timing attacks are concerned,
我想说这些是真的，不仅仅是针对智能卡
I want to mention that these are real.
They're not just about smart cards.
例如，设想一个多核处理器，其中一核运行加密算法
For example, you can imagine a multicore
processor where the encryption algorithm
而攻击者代码却同时在另一核上运行
is running on one core and the attacker
code happens to be running on another
现在这些代码共享同一缓存，于是
core. Now these cores actually share the
same cache. And as a result, an attacker
攻击者可以测量或观测加密算法带来的
can actually measure or can actually look
at the exact cache misses that the
缓存缺失。实际上通过观察这些缓存缺失
encryption algorithm incurred. It turns
out that by looking at cache misses, you
你可以完全解出算法使用的密钥
can completely figure out the secret key
used by the algorithms. So, one core can
一核可以从另一核中提取信息，通过看缓存缺失
essentially extract information from the
other core, just by looking at cache misses.
所以实现这些密码略复杂
So implementing these block ciphers is actually quite subtle
因为必须确保旁道攻击不会
because you have to make sure that the
side channel attacks don't leak
泄漏任何关于密钥的信息
另一类被很多文献讨论的攻击
information about your secret key. Another
type of attack that's been discussed in
叫做错误攻击
the literature is what's called a fault
attack. So here, basically, if you're
攻击智能卡时，可以造成智能卡异常工作
attacking a smart card, you can actually
cause the smart card to malfunction,
可以调高时钟频率，可以加热芯片
perhaps by overclocking it, perhaps by
warming it up. Essentially, you can cause
你可以让这个处理器异常工作，输出错误的数据
the processor to, malfunction, and output
erroneous data. It turns out that, if,
实际上加密时，最后一回合有错误
during encryption, there are errors in the
last round of the encryption process, the
产生的密文就可以暴露密钥K了
resulting ciphertexts that are produced are
enough to actually expose the secret key K.
一个很有意思的结果是，如果有任何错误
That's quite an interesting result that
in fact if you have any errors, if you ever
如果输出了一个错误的结果，那么实际上密钥就暴露了
output a wrong result, that actually could
completely compromise your secret key.
当然，抵抗这种攻击，意味着在输出算法结果前
So, of course, the defense against this means
that before you output the result of your
应当检查以确保计算结果的正确性
algorithm, you should check to make sure
that the correct result was computed.
现在这点是不容易的，因为你怎么知道
Now of course that's nontrivial, because how do
you know that the error didn't happen
你的检查算法有没有发生错误呢？
不过还是有些方法的
in your checking algorithm. But there are
known ways around that. So basically you
你可以计算三次或四次，取结果中占多数的
can actually compute something three or
four times, take the majority over all those
以确保输出是正确的
results, and be assured that the output
really is correct as long as not too many
只要计算中不发生太多错误就行。这些都是针对实现的攻击
faults occurred inside of your computation. These are attacks on the implementation.
希望这些例子能说服大家不仅不要
I hope these examples can assure you that not only should you not
发明自己的分组密码，而且甚至不要去自己实现
invent your own block ciphers, you should
never even implement these crypto
这些密码原型。因为一来，必须确保
primitives yourself. Because (a), you have
to make sure there are no side channel
你的实现没有旁道攻击，而来，必须确保
attachments on your implementation and (b),
you have to make sure that the
实现对错误攻击是安全的。所以
implementation is secure against fault
attacks. Okay so, instead you should just
大家应该只使用标准库，比如OpenSSL等等
use standard libraries like the ones
available in OpenSSL and many other
所以不要自己去实现这些密码原型
libraries out there. So don't implement
these primitives yourself, just use
只使用现有的标准库。好的，现在我想讨论
existing libraries. All right, so now I want
to turn to kind of more sophisticated
一些针对分组密码更为复杂的攻击
我特别讨论一下针对DES的这类攻击
attacks on block ciphers and I'll particularly
talk about how these attacks apply to DES.
好，这些攻击由Biham和Shamir在1989年发现
Okay so these attacks were discovered by
Biham and Shamir back in 1989, and I'll
我还要特别描述1993年松井充发现的一个攻击版本
particularly describe a version of the
attack discovered by Matsui in 1993.
目标是给定很多输入输出对
So the goal here is basically given many,
many input-output pairs, can we actually
我们能否比穷举攻击更好地还原出密钥？
recover the key better than exhaustive
search? So anything that runs better than
任何比穷举更好的攻击都算是分组密码的攻击
exhaustive search already counts as an
attack on the block cipher. Okay, so the
我要说的例子叫做线性密码分析
example I want to give you is what's called
linear cryptanalysis. And here imagine it
试想一下，c是m用密钥k加密得到的
so happens that, you know, c is the
encryption of m using key k, and
如果我看一个随机密钥和随机信息
suppose it so happens that if I look at
random key and a random message, somehow
那么明文和密文之间存在某种依赖
there's a dependence between the message,
ciphertext, and the key bits. In
特别地，如果我逐位异或一组明文
particular, if I XOR a subset of
the message bits, so this is just a
这是一组明文，如果我异或特定的一组密文
subset of the message bits, if I XOR that with a certain subset of the ciphertext
这两组攻击者都能看到
bits. ―So these two the attacker
sees. The attacker has the message and the
攻击者同时有明文和对应密文
然后和密钥的异或进行比较
attacker has the ciphertext. And then you
compare that to an XOR of a subset of
如果这两者是完全独立的
the key bits. Now if the two were
completely independent which is what you'd
我们当然不想能用明文和密文
like, you definitely don't want your
message and your ciphertext to somehow
就能用某种方式预测密钥
如果两者是完全独立的
predict your key bits, if the two are
like, completely independent, then this
那么这个等式成立的概率就严格地为1/2
equality will hold with probability
exactly one-half. But suppose it so
设想有一点不均匀导致这个等式以概率
happens that there's a bias and this
probability holds with probability half
(口误probability->equality)
1/2加上某个小Epsilon成立。事实上，对DES
plus epsilon for some small epsilon. It so
happens that, in fact, for DES, there is
有这么个关系。这个关系之所以成立
such a relation. The relation holds
specifically because of a bug in the design
是因为第5个S盒子的设计有点问题
事实上第5个S盒子有点太接近线性函数了
of the fifth S-box. It turns out the fifth
S-box happens to be too close to a linear
那个线性函数传遍了整个
function. And that linear function,
basically, as it propagates through the
DES的计算过程，产生了这么一个关系
entire DES circuit, generates a relation
of this type. You notice, this is
注意这里计算的是一个线性关系
basically a linear relation that's being
computed here. So, this small tiny, tiny
第5个S盒子的微弱的线性关系会对整个算法产生这个关系
linearity in the fifth S-box generates
this relation over the entire circuit,
这里Epsilon是很小的，约1除以2的21次方
where the epsilon is tiny. Epsilon is one
over 2^21, and I wrote down what
写在这了。这个不均匀很微小，但是
that is. So the bias is really, really,
really small. But nevertheless, there is a
使用这些特定位，也有不均匀发生
bias using these particular subsets of bits. Now, I'm not going to show you how to
现在我不推导这个关系，也不告诉大家这是什么意思
derive this relation, or I'm not going to show you even what it is. I'll just tell you
我只说怎么怎么使用这么个找到的关系
好的，这是我们的关系
how to use a relation like this once you find it. Okay. So here's our relation
问题是怎么使用它。那么用一点统计的知识
that we have. And the question is how to
use it. So with a little bit of statistics
(参考 二项分布)
你可以使用像这样的一个方程来决定某些位
you can actually use an equation like this
to determine some of the key bits. And
这么做：假设你有1除以Epsilon的平方那么多个明文密文对
here's you do it. Suppose you were given one over epsilon squared message-ciphertext pairs.
这些必须是互相独立的随机明文和对应密文
And these have to be
independently random messages and the
应用这上面的公式
corresponding ciphertexts. What you would
do is you would use the formula above. In
事实上你可以使用公式左边来计算这个
fact you would use the left-hand side of
the formula above to compute this relation
明文和密文之间的关系，用所有你有的明文密文对
between the message and ciphertext for
all the pairs you were given. Now what do
怎么办？对于这些值中一半加上Epsilon的值
you know? You know that for half plus
epsilon of these values, you know that
这些值等于密钥各个位的异或
these things will be equal to an
XOR of the key bits. So if you
所有如果取你计算所得的所有值中的大多数
take majority over all the values you've
computed, it turns out it's not so
不难看出事实上你的这种对密钥所有位异或的预测
difficult to see that in fact you'll get
the correct prediction for the XOR of the
以97.7%的概率是正确的。换句话说
如果这个关系在多于一半的时间里是正确的
key bits with a probability of 97.7%. In
other words, if this relation happens to
那么大多数的结果将是正确的
be correct more than half the time, then
the majority will be right. And because
因为有不均匀Epsilon，以多于一半，99.7%的概率
there's a bias, there's an epsilon bias, the probability that you will be correct
我们的预测是正确的
more than half the time is, in fact,
97.7%. In which case, the majority, in
这里大多数的结果，会给你正确的密钥所有位的异或
对吧？是不是很不错
fact, will give you the correct XOR of the
key bits. Okay? So this is kinda cool.
在1除以Epsilon平方的次数内，你可以解出
Within one over epsilon squared time, you
can figure out an XOR of a bunch of key
密钥所有位的异或。现在，我们把它应用到DES
DES的Epsilon等于1除以2的21次方
bits. So now, let's apply this to DES.
So, for DES, we have epsilon, which is one
意思是如果给我2的42次方个输入输出对
over 2^21. Which means that if you give me
2^42 input-output pairs, I can
我可以解出密钥所有位的异或值。实际上我告诉大家
figure out an XOR of the key bits. And now,
it turns out, I'm not gonna exactly show
不严格地讲，使用这个方法，你还不知道密钥中任何一位
you how, roughly speaking, using this
method, you don't just get one key bit. In
事实上，你可以取密钥中任意两位，也可以使用这个方法
fact, you get two key bits. You can kind
of use this relation. One's going in a
一个向前，一个向后
forward direction and one's going in a
backwards direction. So that gives you two
这样就给你一些密钥中这两位的异或值
好，这样就有了密钥中两位的信息了
XORs of bits of the secret key. Okay, so
that's two bits of information about the
其实你还可以获得另外12位
secret key. And then it turns out you can
get twelve more bits, because,
因为你可以解出第5个S盒子的输入
essentially, you can figure out what the
inputs are to the fifth S-box. Okay, so,
那么我就不细说具体过程了。但其实是可以得到另外12位的
I'm not going to exactly show you how. But it
turns out you can get twelve more bits,
这样一共就14位了。现在，使用这个方法
which is a total of fourteen bits overall.
So now, using this method, you've
你已经还原了密钥中的14位内容
当然，这需要2的42次方的时间
recovered fourteen bits of the secret key.
And of course, it took you time 2^42.
好，然后干什么？剩下的就很简单了
Okay, so then, what do you do?
Well, so the rest of it is easy. Now what
你只需要穷举密钥中剩下的位就可以了
you're going to do is you're going to do
exhaustive search on the remaining bits.
还剩下多少位呢？有42位
Well how many remaining bits are there?
Well, there are 42 remaining bits, so
穷举密钥也会花掉2的42次方的时间。那么一共攻击所花时间是多少？
the exhaustive search will take you time 2^42. So what's the total attack time?
攻击的第一步，确定14位需要2的42次方的时间
Well, the first step of the algorithm
to determine the fourteen bits took 2^42 time,
剩下位的穷举需要另一个2的42次方的时间
and the remaining brute force
search also took 2^42 time.
所以整个攻击需要2的43次方的时间，对吧？
So overall, the attack took two to the 43
time. Okay? So now, this is much better
这比穷举攻击好很多了。在2的43次方时间里
我们破解了DES。不过当然
than exhaustive search. Within two to the
43 time, we broke DES. But of course, this
这需要2的42次方个输入输出对
required two to the 42 random input-output
pairs whereas exhaustive search only
而穷举攻击只需要3对。好，这里要求的明文密文对
required three pairs. Okay, so this is a
fairly large number of input-output
数目还是很多的，但给了这么多
pairs that are needed, but given such a
large number, you can actually recover the
确实可以更快地还原DES密钥。好，这里的教训是什么？
key faster than exhaustive search. Okay,
so what's the lesson in all this?
第一，任何细微的线性关系
The lesson is, firstly, any tiny bit of
linearity, basically, in this― in the
比如这里第5个S盒子没有其他S盒子设计得好
fifth S-box, which was not designed as
well as the other S-boxes, basically led
就导致了一种攻击算法。好，任一细微的线性关系
to an attack on the algorithm. Okay. A tiny
bit of linearity already introduced this
都会引入线性攻击。再强调一下
linear attack. And I want to emphasize
again that this is not the sort of thing
这些不是在设计密码时你就能考虑到的。所以结论是
you would think of when you design a cipher. And so again, the conclusion here is,
对分组密码有很复杂的攻击，仅凭自己一人
there are very subtle attacks on block
ciphers, ones which you will not be able to
往往是无法找到的。所以说要坚持使用标准
find yourself. And so just stick to the
standards. Don't ever, ever, ever, ever
永远不要自己设计分组密码。好，这就是
我想说的关于分组密码的复杂攻击
design your block cipher. Okay, so that's
all I want to say about sophisticated
现在我们看最后一种根据
attacks. Now let's move on to the last
type of attack that I want to mention, which
我称之为量子攻击，它对分组密码是通用的
I'll call quantum attacks, which are
again― these are generic attacks on
我来解释一下什么意思
all block ciphers. So let me explain what
I mean by this.
首先我们看一个普遍的问题，一个普遍的搜索问题
So first of all, let's look at a generic problem, a generic search problem. Suppose I have a function
假设我有一个定义在大集合X上的函数，输出有两种值，0或1
on some large domain X, that happens to be
two outputs, either zero or one.
这个函数的值大部分都是0
And it so happens that this function is mostly
zero. And there's, like, maybe one input
也许只有一个输入，所对应的函数值为1
where the function happens to evaluate to
one. And your goal is basically, you know,
目标是找出这些输入，满足函数值为1
find me the inputs where the function
happens to be one. Maybe there's only one
可能只有一个这样的输入。但目标是找到它
那么在一台经典的计算机上
such input. But your goal is to find it.
Well, so on a classical computer, what can
你能做什么呢？函数给你了，作为一个黑盒
you do? The function is given to you. It's
given to you as a black box. So the best
你能做的最好的只能是尝试所有可能的输入
you can do is just try all possible
inputs. So this is gonna take time which
所以需要的时间和定义域的大小是线性相关的
现在，实际上却有一个绝对魔法的结果
in linear in the size of the domain. Now,
it turns out there's an absolutely magical
告诉我们如果你构建了一台基于量子物理的计算机
result that says that if you build a
computer that's based on quantum physics
而非经典物理的话，那么你可以更快地解决这个问题
as opposed to classical physics, you can
solve this problem faster. So let me
那么让我解释这个的意义。首先在20世纪七八十年代
explain what I mean by this. So first of
all in the 70s and 80s it was observed, I
我想实际上是Richard Feynman最早观察到
think it was actually Richard Feynman who observed this initially, that said
实际上在经典计算机上模拟量子实验是非常困难的
that it turns out to be very difficult to
simulate quantum experiments on a
所以Feyman说，如果是这样的话
classical computer. So Feynman said, if
that's the case, maybe these quantum
也许这些量子实验是经典计算机所无法计算的东西
experiments are computing things that a
classical computer can't compute.
所有某种意义上它们可以计算得很快
So they're somehow able to compute very
quickly things that are very difficult to
而同样的问题经典计算机很难做到。这是正确的，事实上
do classically. And that turned out to be
correct. And in fact, the example I want
我想给大家看的例子是这些惊奇事实中的一个
事实上，如果你可以构建一个量子计算机
to show you is one of these amazing things that in fact, if you could build a
用于计算量子物理，那么它可以被用来
quantum computer that's using quantum
physics, then it's, in fact, you can solve
解决这个搜索问题，用不着|X|的时间
而是|X|的平方根的时间即可
this search problem not in time X but in
time square root of X. So somehow, even
即使计算机不知道任何函数F的信息
though the computer doesn't know anything
about the function F, it's treating it as
F被视为黑盒，但是，依然可以找到一个点，其函数值为1
a black box, nevertheless, it's able to
find a point where the function is one, in
在|X|的平方根的时间内。我不想在这里解释为什么
time square root of X. I'm not going to explain this here, but, at the end of the
(参见 Grover算法)
在本课程结尾，我们会有个高级课题讲座
class, we're gonna have an advanced topics
lecture. And if you'd like me to explain
(可能是第二季了)
届时我会解释这个算法的工作过程
how this algorithm works, I can explain it
in that advanced topics lecture.
这是很有趣的，事实上，量子计算机对密码学
It's actually quite interesting, and, in fact,
quantum computers have quite an impact on
影响很大。我说了，我在最后一讲解释这个量子算法
crypto. And again, as I said, I can
explain this in the very last lecture.
好的，那这和破解分组密码有何关系呢？
All right. So what does this have to do with
breaking block cyphers? So far it's just a
目前这仅仅是个普遍问题。
噢，在谈应用之前我还要说一点
generic search problem. Well, oh actually
I should say before I show you the
大家可以想知道
application, I should mention that, well,
you might be wondering, well, can someone
能不能制造量子计算机？这个还完全不知道
build a quantum computer. And this is
still completely unknown. At this point,
目前没人知道我们是否能够构造量子计算机
nobody really knows if we can build
large enough quantum computers to actually
来利用这个漂亮的Grover算法提供的优势
take advantage of this beautiful algorithm
due to Grover. Alright, so what does this
好，这和分组密码有何关系？假设给你一个明文密文对
have to do with block ciphers? Well, so
suppose I give you a message-ciphertext pair.
一个或几个。我们可以如下定义一个函数
Just one or just a few. We can
define a function as follows. It's a
这是一个定义在密钥空间K上的函数
function on K, it's a function on, the key
space. And the function will basically
这个函数会在k处输出1，如果正好满足用k加密m得到c
output one if it so happens that the
encryption of m with k maps to c, and it
否则函数输出0。现在我们说这个函数
will output zero otherwise. Now we argue
that basically this is exactly the type of
正是在密钥空间中一点处为1
function that's one at one point in the
key space and that's it. So by Grover's
那么根据Grover算法，我们可以找到密钥
用|K|的平方根的时间
algorithm, we can actually find the secret
key in time square root of K.
什么意思？对于DES，这可以完全摧毁DES了
So what does that mean? For DES, this would
totally destroy DES. This would say
这仅用时2的28次方，就能找出密钥！
2的28次方仅为2亿
that in time 2^28, you could
find a key. 2^28 is about 200 million.
现代计算机上2亿步只需毫秒级
So 200 million steps which is, you know, just takes a millisecond on a modern computer.
(这样讲有点夸张了)
足以摧毁DES了，即便是AES的128位密钥
This would totally destroy DES. But even AES with 128-bit keys,
你也可以仅用2的64次方的时间，就可以找到密钥
you would be able to find the secret
key in time, roughly 2^64.
2的64次方的时间，在今天也算不安全的
And 2^64 is these days, considered
insecure. That's within the realm of
它还在穷举法的范围内。所以，如果有人可以造量子计算机
exhaustive search. And so, basically, if
somebody was able to build a quantum
我们说AES128不再安全！
computer, we would then say that AES-128
is no longer secure. Instead, if somebody,
如果明天的报纸上你能看到文章说
you know, if tomorrow, you open up the
newspaper, and you read an article that
某某造出量子计算机了
says, you know, so-and-so built a
quantum computer, the conclusion, the
那就可以下结论，大家必须立刻使用256位密钥的分组密码了
consequence of all that is that you should
immediately move to block ciphers that use
因为256为密钥的Grover算法运行时间是2的128次方
256 bits, because then the running time
of Grover's algorithm is 2^128,
目前还是安全的很
which is more time than we consider
feasible, and the, basically there are
有256位的密码的，比如AES256
example ciphers with 256 bits, for
example, AES-256. This is one of the
这也是AES要设计256位密钥的原因之一
reasons why AES was designed with 256
bits in mind. But to be honest, this is
但其实不是唯一的原因，还有其他原因的
not the only reason. There are other reasons why you want it to have larger key sizes.
完事，我说过，这只是带大家初尝针对分组密码的不同攻击
Okay, so this is, as I said, just a taste of the different attacks on block ciphers,
暂告一段落了。如果我们决定最后一讲讨论量子算法
and I'm gonna leave it at that. If we decide on quantum for the last
我们最后还会来看Grover算法的
topic of the course, then we'll recover
that in the very last lecture.